http://youtu.be/u9UUVh8YoEg
Tung Dinh_VGU http://youtu.be/u9UUVh8YoEg
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's take a look at the last piece off the ISA
Giờ ta cùng tới phần cuối cùng của ISA
which is the memory map.
là tổ chức memory
As you saw, there are different kinds of memory.
Có nhiều loại memory
There's the RAM, there is the ROM, or the Flash, and there could be multiple
RAM, ROM hoặc là Flash,
ROMs on a system.
và cũng có multiple ROMs trong hệ thống
And so as a convenience, we want to refer to all of them as if they were
Và để thuận tiện, ta có thể truy xuất tất cả nếu chúng là
part of a single table.
phần trong bảng này
That is, we want to refer to them by their location.
Ta có thể truy xuất chúng bằng location
So what we do is we refer to memory on the ARM ISA by a 32-bit address.
Vậy, memory được truy xuất trên ARM ISA bằng 1 address 32-bit
So the addresses start from, again I am using the convenient shortcut,
Address bắt đầu từ, đơn giản thì
which is 0x00000000, with eight zeroes, that's the
từ x00000000, với 8 số 0
lowest memory location.
Đó là cái address thấp nhất
And the farthest, or the highest memory location, is 0xFFFFFFFF.
Và cái address nhớ cao nhất là 0xFFFFFFFF
Now, the total memory we can refer to is sometimes called the address space.
Tổng memory có thể truy xuất được thì đôi khi gọi là address space
The address space constitutes the number of locations.
Address space tạo ra số các địa chỉ
We can refer to.
Ta có thể truy xuất
With 32-bit address, we can refer from 0x00000000, eight zeros, all the way
với address 32-bit, ta có thể truy xuất từ 0x00000000, 8 số 0
up to eight F's.
cho tới 8 số F
Each location is going to hold eight bits of information.
mỗi location sẽ giữ 8 bits thông tin
So we say that each location holds eight bits of information, so memory
Ta nói rằng, mỗi location giữ
location zero holds eight bits of information and every location holds
memory location 0 giữ 8 bits thông tin và mọi location đều giữ
eight bits of information.
8 bits thông tin
Which is one byte.
Mà là 1 byte
Now let's take a look at the various banks within the memory.
Rồi, hãy xem nhiều phần nhớ trong memory
So the memory itself is composed of a region of memory which starts
Memory được cấu thành từ các vùng của memory
from zero all the way up to a location which is 0x0003FFFF which makes up
bắt đầu từ 0 hết, cho đến location 0x0003FFFF
256k of Flash or ROM.
tạo ra 256k Flash hoặc ROM
This is where we're going to write our code.
Đây là chỗ để viết code
So this is the part where we are going to put our code, constants,
Đây là phần để bỏ code, constants,
and stuff like that.
và những thứ như vậy vào
Code which is our instructions and constants.
code, là instruction, và constants
Now, we have our next bank of memory, which is going to be our RAM.
Giờ thì ta tới phần nhớ tiếp theo của memory đó là RAM
This is the 32k of RAM on the board that we are using, which starts at
Đây là 32k RAM trên board mà ta sử dụng, bắt đầu từ
memory location 0x20000000 all the way up to 0x20007FFF This is the RAM where
memory location 0x20000000 cho tới 0x20007FFFF
we will store our data, our variables, and again this is the volatile part.
Đây là RAM mà ta sẽ lưu data, variables RAM sẽ không được lưu khi tắt máy
And also our stack is going to be part of this region.
stack cũng sẽ nằm trong RAM
And now we have our all-important part of the memory map, which is the I/O.
Ta cũng có phần nhớ vô cùng quan trọng đó là I/O
Now you may be wondering why we are looking at the memory and talking
Bạn cũng có thể hỏi tại sao lại là memory
about I/O. Well, this it's important to understand that the way we refer to
và nói về I/O. Thật ra, chúng quan trọng vì liên quan đến
I/O devices, again this I/O starts at 0x40000000 and goes all the way up to
cách truy xuất thiết bị nhập xuất, phần I/O này bắt đầu từ 0x40000000 và cho đến
0x400FFFFF.
0x400FFFFF
But we refer to I/O using a technique called memory-mapped I/O.
Nhưng, ta lại truy xuất I/O bằng memory-mapped I/O
So the idea of memory-mapped I/O is when we want to refer to a device, we
Ý tưởng của memory-mapped I/O là khi ta cần truy xuất thiết bị
simply read or write a particular location in memory, and that
chỉ cần read hoặc write 1 location xác định trong memory
particular location in turn, for example, if I read manipulating a
ví dụ, nếu tôi read thao tác 1 port nào đó
particular port I would go to this location in memory and a particular
tôi sẽ tới location này, và bit xác định này
bit here might refer to an I/O pin.
để truy xuất pin I/O
And manipulating this bit is the equivalent of
và thao tác trên bit này thì tương đương với
manipulating this I/O pin.
thao tác trên pin I/O này
So this is what memory-mapped I/O gives us.
Tóm lại, đậy là memory-mapped I/O
Now there are some other I/O. Some of these locations have other
Cũng có những I/O khác. Một số location lại có thông tin khác
information, not all of them refer to pins, so in general then these will
không phải đều truy xuất pins, nói chung, những locations này
refer to, these locations will refer to device registers.
dùng để truy xuất registers của thiết bị
And there's more I/O, and there is more I/O which is the internal I/O, as
Và còn nhiều I/O khác, mà là I/O nội
opposed to the external ones that have something to do with external
nó ngược với lại I/O ngoại mà thao tác với các register ngoại
registers, external devices of some kind.
thiết bị ngoại vi
This starts from 0xE0000000 and goes all the way up to 0xE004FFFF.
bắt đầu từ 0xE0000000 và cho tới 0xE004FFFF
So what we notice in the memory map is that we have a lot of, there are
Ta chú ý đến memory map,
several sections of the memory.
nơi có nhiều vùng nhớ
And we have these 256k of ROM, 32k of RAM, I/O ports, internal I/O. And if
ta có 256k ROM, 32k RAM, cổng I/O và I/O nội
you notice that there are chunks of space in between that I have not
và bạn chú ý đến những đoạn ở giữa mà tôi
referred to.
không đề cập đến
Well these chunks of space in between are unused in that we don't have any
Những đoạn ở giữa này không được dùng tới, vì ta không thể
way of accessing them.
truy cập chúng được
And making accesses to these locations are considered errors.
Truy cập những locations này gây ra lỗi
Now what is also the case is that this picture obviously is not to scale.
Đây không phải để mở rộng quy mô
Notice that the 32k of RAM that we have here and the 256k ROM leave out
Chú ý rằng 32k RAM ở đây và 256k ROM
whole chunks off empty space in between.
chừa ra những khoẳng trống ở giữa
And so as a convenience, I'm showing this as if they're at all contiguous,
Để thuận tiện, tôi nói chúng nối tiếp nhau
and they are of a certain size, but in reality there is a lot of empty space
và có cùng kích thước, nhưng thực ra, có rất nhiều khoảng trống
that we are referring to.
mà ta đề cập đến
So now in this module we looked at a lot of important fundamental concepts.
Do đó, trong module này, ta quan tâm đến những khái niệm quan trọng
These were concepts that we expect you to understand and remember as you go
Cái mà bạn phải hiểu và nhớ để học tiếp
forward, because we looked at number systems that allow you
bởi, ta đang hướng tới các hệ thống
to represent things.
để bạn biểu đạt
We looked at the guts of an embedded system, what's a microcontroller, and
Ta quan tâm tới cái tâm của hệ thống nhúng là microcontroller,
what is the ISA of a processor, we looked at the memory,
thế nào là ISA của processor, memory,
we looked at registers.
registers
Now all this will only make sense if we do something with it.
Tất cả đều ý nghĩa, nếu bạn làm gì đó
So what we are going to do from this point onwards is get our hands dirty
Do đó, bắt đầu từ bây giờ, bạn phải nhúng tay vào làm
and have fun.
và chúc vui!